[Music]
welcome to this business Central launch
event session watch new in server and
database this is uh the fourth session
in in this series and in this session
we're going to talk about report in
capabilities the first thing is data
analysis on queries yes the query object
has been there for 10 years and it's
time that it gets a bit more prominence
so now you've always been able to open
the query URL now it has the new uh
analysis view attached and you can also
run it directly in the UI because we now
have support for the Run
object
and it means that you can add it to
pages and it in this case an item hero
query and then it'll show up as an
action you can invoke which will open a
page showing the result of the query and
from there you can do all the nice
things that you can do in analysis views
with uh grouping and pivoting and stuff
like that excellent new addition can we
can we talk a little bit about under the
hood here yeah yeah so imagine so you
can see this screenshot here with a UI
on a query right this means this the a
runtime is able to apparently run
queries and also if you think of it
pivot and filter on queries which means
that we can actually under like in the a
runtime not in Al API but just below
that we can do Dynamic query
capabilities
yes and now it will be covered more in
detail in another session another thing
we've added is the ability to handle
large amounts of data the way we do
these queries is that each drill down is
a query by itself so that you can now do
the sum of millions of records and then
general ledger entry and D do drill down
using uh server side analysis views
which now also works on
queries so if you listen Clos
here this is something interesting going
on in the a runtime and we won't talk
anymore about that this is not the no
this is not the session you're thinking
of so for Excel layouts um the Excel
layouts feature did not really handle
parent child overiew detail types very
well because it was following the logic
of RDL reports where the data set was Al
always a Square data set now we've made
a change so that if you have multiple
root data items then the data for these
can now be represented in each their
sheet which gives you a much more
condensed view if you look at the one to
the left you will actually see that the
real data is down along the diagonal
line and the rest was filled out with
other values basically the uh null value
values to make it a square data set
making the handling of this in Excel
code quite
cumbersome but if you set the Excel
layer multiple data sheets to true then
a sheet will be generated with the data
item names instead of just having one
square data set
exactly now if you think about that
inside Excel and maybe use some of the
more modern tools in Excel modern here
meaning 10 years
old you have basically two interesting
modeling tool inside Excel you have
power query which is a way to modify
data to transform data it's actually a
small ETL language in itself and then
you have power pivot which is a modeling
tool inside Excel to Define
relationships uh between tables and this
makes this new
feature is is you can use both of these
Excel features to really make a
compelling data model for your Excel
layouts that allows you to do crazy
things I would say not crazy we like
crazy great things um so we we we really
looking forward to seeing how will this
impact the your Excel skills maybe you
need to up them a little bit and learn
about these new um or other ways of
modeling data in Excel which by the way
are the same as same engine as
powerp um so the new property on reports
is called Excel layout multiple data
sheets available in version 23 if you
set it to true you get these new
multiple data sheets in your Excel uh
layouts when they're being rendered and
if you set this to something that does
not use an Excel layout it actually has
no effect but we've found that it works
a lot better if you target your report
to the type of layout you want whether
it's RDL word or Excel so this is
relevant for the reports that you're
targeting to be consumed in
Excel while we were here we uh we also
worked on making teaching tips and help
links available both on queries and
Report request Pages the latter it was
actually already there we just never
talked about it and documented it so now
it's it's there please help your users
understand the the intent of reports and
queries and give them some proper help
links because a report and or a query is
just as useful or an first class citizen
as normal functionality so why shouldn't
we also help the users out
here this is how it looks uh a teaching
tip on a request page and by the way um
if you use the context sensitive Health
page you you can make dedicated uh help
links for your reports and the teaching
tips um about text and title also uh
comes if you open help so start using
that and create awesome reports and
create awesome reports as well uh same
thing goes for queries so this is an
your analyze inventory query that now
has a nice nice teaching tip by the way
the teaching tip is also after you you
close it you can always just hover over
the title and get it back and then the
same thing applies both for teaching
tips and for helpl Lings that for
queries they will now now be available
um in the help
pain to kind of help you we also uh
worked on the reports documentation so
there's a lot more going on here so go
and visit this over the next months and
we'll try to to to make that better also
adding ways to create robust reports and
robust layouts something we're working
on right now so that should hopefully be
in the doc over the next month and
specifically for Excel go to the BC
Excel samples uh site where you have
tips and tricks for how to design your
data sets and layouts sample layout out
for existing reports you can just try
out and also see the techniques that are
being used if you want to do
presentations on this topic for events
or conferences there are sample powerbi
no PowerPoint decks here uh FAQ and list
of videos If videos is the way you learn
things so Goos for
reporting the first most important thing
is you need to start thinking about
reporting in a different way you need to
to stop just developing reports and
instead understand what is the user
trying to do with analytics and based on
that start supporting whatever they want
if they want a report that is being
printed maybe develop a report if they
just want to consume in Excel do an
Excel layout if they want to consume in
client write a query if they want kpis
do powerbi
which is also the next thing you
probably should start learn a little bit
about powerbi bi business intelligence
and er are closely
related ER is about business processes
business intelligence is about reporting
and and and getting insights into
business processes they go together and
powerbi is here to stay and it's going
to be the tool of choice especially for
for for kpis on business Central
yeah and then you should also invest in
Al queries they're not only for
performance tuning you can use them to
generate really good analysis views they
are very powerful to actually join data
together from multiple sources and allow
the user to the freedom to slice and
dice as the user wants so sometimes
instead of building a report it might
just mean that you should build a query
instead and then use the analysis view
instead of investing in reporting and
then also learn how to design to design
for Excel
layouts and very often just having a
good report data set and a good first
layout allows the customer to add what
they need in the layout because we find
that there are a lot more people who can
do excel layouts than RDL layouts
surprise surprise surprise so sometimes
instead of buil me report it might just
mean buil me a report data set which is
good for Excel reports and you know what
yens I think that once you do this you
would have customers that um like
Wizards in Excel and you might learn
something from your customers here I
didn't know you could do that Excel it
will blow your minds and you will uh
learn together with your
customer so two in at least two relevant
sessions that you might want to jump to
out out of this um apart from of course
the serus of four there are two sessions
what's new in powerbi and reporting for
developers is something where we go
deeper into this thinking about the
analytics requirements and then pick
different tools also we have some new
cool things going on in powerbi embed so
uh so if you want this content you
definitely want to check this session
out and the second session is about um
this data analysis this feature that is
now generally available on lists and
queries this second session is much more
about the how you should think of this
as a functional consultant for end users
and then of course we refer to the
general business Central resources
Yammer X U BC ideas and if you can join
some of the office hours and with that
thank you very much for watching
thanks